Steven Stupak Papers VHP2003/1
CCSU Veterans History Project
Steven S. Stupak papers
Bulk, 1942-1945
1942-1945, 2003
VHP2003/1
CCSU Veterans History Project
40.0 Digital objects 1 interview DVD
This collection details Steven Stupak’s experiences as a Flight Engineer and Prisoner of War during World War II. A 97 minute taped interview was conducted on December 18, 2003 at Central Connecticut State University by Eileen Hurst. Along with Mr. Stupak’s taped interview the collection contains reproductions of scanned personal and military manuscripts, photographs, and correspondence dating from 1942 to 1945. These materials describe bombing missions, interactions between American and German service men, and conditions in German and Polish POW camps. Local news articles and publications from 2004 and 2005 document veteran recognition programs and observances in Connecticut.
Steven Stupak
Biography
A native of Lopez, Pennsylvania, Steven Stupak enitemed in the Army Air Corps on Jan 7, 1942, and served as a member of the 94th Bomber Group. While assigned to the 8th Air Force Base as a Flight Engineer he was a member of the 331st Bomber Squadron. Technical Sergeant Steven Stupak was shot down over Germany on October 7, 1944 and spent time in German and Polish Prisoner of War camps. For his bravery and courageous efforts during World War II, he received the Air Medal with one cluster, and the Purple Heart. Steven was discharged on Oct 14, 1945.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
This collection details Steven Stupak’s experiences as a Flight Engineer and Prisoner of War during World War II. A 97 minute taped interview was conducted on December 18, 2003 at Central Connecticut State University by Eileen Hurst. Along with Mr. Stupak’s taped interview the collection contains reproductions of scanned personal and military manuscripts, photographs, and correspondence dating from 1942 to 1945. These materials describe bombing missions, interactions between American and German service men, and conditions in German and Polish POW camps. Local news articles and publications from 2004 and 2005 document veteran recognition programs and observances in Connecticut.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged based on content and material type into 4 series:
Series I, Personal papers
Series II, Military documents
Series III, Publications
Series IV, Multi-media
Restrictions on Access
Open for research
Online Access
An Online exhibition of this veteran's papers can be accessed at project's website
Custodial History note
All manuscripts and photographs donated were digitzed and digitally preserved. The donor retained all original manuscripts and photographs.
United States. Army Air Forces. Bombardment Squadron, 331st.; England; Germany; Interviews; Manuscript; Photographs; Poland; Stalag Luft IV; Veterans - - Connecticut - - interviews; World War II - - Personal Narrative, American; World War, 1939-1945 - - Prisoners and prisons, German
- Series I, Personal Papers, VHP2003/1.I
  - Post Card to parents, Dec. 25, 1944; VHP2003/1.I.1
  - Interview Synopsis, Dec 18, 2003; VHP2003/1.I.2
  - Army Air Force Certificate of Appreciation for War Service, undate; VHP2003/1.I.3
  - Pin-up picture, undate; VHP2003/1.I.4
- Series II, Military Documents, VHP2003/1.II
  - Telegram to Mrs. Stupak regarding Steven’s MIA status, Oct. 25.1944; VHP2003/1.II.1
  - Telegram to Mrs. Stupak regarding Steven’s POW status, Dec. 11.1944; VHP2003/1.II.2
- Series III, Publications, VHP2003/1.III
  - Prisoners of War Remember (Herald article), Sept. 15.2004; VHP2003/1.III.1
  - Voices of Connecticut Veterans: Steven Stupak and the German Death March (Connecticut History, Vol. 44, No. 1 article), Spring 2005; VHP2003/1.III.2
  - Open Letter to the Public, Sept. 16, 2005; VHP2003/1.III.3
- Series IV, Multi-Media, VHP2003/1.IV
  - Subseries A, Still Images, VHP2003/1.IVa
    - Steven Stupak, Army Air Corps Service photograph, 1942; VHP2003/1.IVa.1
    - Steven Stupak in uniform, Feb. 28, 1943; VHP2003/1.IVa.2
    - Steven Stupak (standing, far left) and training crew, Avon Park, FL, 1943; VHP2003/1.IVa.3
    - Steven Stupak and a group of Army Air Corp personnel the night before shipping overseas, undate; VHP2003/1.IVa.4
    - Steven Stupak and his flight squad, undate; VHP2003/1.IVa.5
    - Portrait of Steven Stupak drawn by British POW Leftie Maddox, Dec 24,1944; VHP2003/1.IVa.6
    - Portrait of John Stacco drawn by British POW Leftie Maddox, Dec 24,1944; VHP2003/1.IVa.7
  - Subseries B, Moving Images, VHP2003/1.IVb
    - Oral History interview with Steven Stupak, Dec. 18,2003; VHP2003/1.IVb.1 (Disk DVD VHP2003/1, Box Circulation 1)